<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An examination of Dr. Balyes five waies whereby he endeavours to prove the Church of Rome to be the only church of Christ wherein salvation is to be had, and the Church of England to be no true church. By Robert Seppens rector of Hingham in Norfolk.</title>
            <author>Seppens, Robert.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1679</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 46 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 19 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A92921</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S2558A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R229928</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99896383</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99896383</idno>
            <idno type="VID">154352</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A92921)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 154352)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2413:7)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An examination of Dr. Balyes five waies whereby he endeavours to prove the Church of Rome to be the only church of Christ wherein salvation is to be had, and the Church of England to be no true church. By Robert Seppens rector of Hingham in Norfolk.</title>
                  <author>Seppens, Robert.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>35, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by M[ary]. C[larke]. for William Oliver, bookseller, in the market-place in Norwich,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1679.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from Wing CD.</note>
                  <note>Copy filmed at UMI microfilm Early English Books 1641-1700 reel 2413 has leaf A4 torn away.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Church of England --  Apologetic works --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:154352:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AN EXAMINATION OF Dr. <hi>Balyes</hi> Five Waies, WHEREBY He endeavours to prove the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> to be the only Church of Chriſt wherein Salvation is to be had, and the Church of <hi>England</hi> to be no True Church.</p>
            <p>BY <hi>ROBERT SEPPENS</hi> Rector of <hi>Hingham</hi> in <hi>Norfolk.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed by <hi>M. C.</hi> for <hi>William Oliver,</hi> Bookſeller, in the Market-Place in <hi>Norwich.</hi> 1679.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:154352:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:154352:2"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen King <hi>CHARLES</hi> the Firſt, that glorious Martyr, of ever bleſſed memory, was by his inhuman and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natural Subjects moſt barbarouſly Murdered; there were Miſsionaries from <hi>Rome</hi> employed in all parts of the Kingdom to diſaffect the people to the Monarchy, and the Hierarchy, to the Religion, and the Government of the Kingdom Eſtabliſhed by Law. Amongſt the reſt, one came to a Gentlewoman not far from me (when I lived at <hi>Bradenham</hi>) and preſented her with a Book, Stiled <hi>An End to all Controverſies,</hi> of which Doctor <hi>Baly</hi> was the Author. Now Doctor <hi>Baly</hi> you muſt know was revolted from the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and was had in great eſteem for two famous Books formerly Publiſhed by him. One was a Romance Dedicated to the Lady <hi>Crane</hi> of <hi>Suffolk,</hi> Entituled <hi>Herba Parietis, or the Wall Flower;</hi> the other was <hi>A Narrative of the Conference betwixt King</hi> Charles <hi>the Firſt, and the Marqueſs of</hi> Worceſter <hi>at</hi> Ragland <hi>Caſtle.</hi> It is not my preſent buſineſs to enquire how well he diſcharged himſelf in thoſe his undertakings. But certainly the laſt Book he Publiſhed, <hi>viz. An End to all Controverſies,</hi> and
<pb facs="tcp:154352:3"/>that indeed which was given to the foremention'd Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlewoman in order to ſome further deſign upon her: was <hi>palmarium opus,</hi> the moſt worthy of the three. The Gentlewoman after the peruſal of it brought it to me, with an earneſt deſire to hear my judgment of it, to ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie, therefore, her requeſt, I Read it over, and in the Reading of it, I obſerved it conſiſted of theſe two parts eſpecially, A Calumnious invective againſt the Church of <hi>England;</hi> then a Polemick Diſcourſe, wherein the Doctor by Five Arguments had there endeavoured to prove the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> to be the only true Church wherein Life and Salvation was to be had, and the Church of <hi>England</hi> to be no true Church. The Gentlewoman ſoon perceived what dangerous Conſequence this Book might be of, and ſo was not infected with any of thoſe pernicious Principles contained in it. But I fearing leſt through the weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of her Sex (though indeed ſhe was Prudent, Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous, and in matters of Religion of underſtanding a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove her Sex) ſhe might have been prevail'd upon by thoſe Arguments, and being very much concern'd to deliver her from the danger and poyſon of them, I thought my ſelf oblig'd to commend an Antidote to her to prevent infecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. To effect which I paſſed by the Railing invective part of his Diſcourſe, and made it my buſineſs to Anſwer the Polemick part of it; wherein though he very confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently boaſts of his Arguments as unanſwerable and invin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cible, yet after a ſtrict enquiry and examination of them, I neither found <hi>Hector</hi> nor <hi>Achilles</hi> in them. This Diſcourſe I Penned long ſince, and immediately after de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered
<pb facs="tcp:154352:3"/>it my ſelf to the forementioned Perſon, who liv'd to ſee the happy Reſtoration of His Majeſty, and then dyed in the Communion of the Church of <hi>England.</hi> I long expected ſome Anſwer to this, but hearing of none I have now ventur'd to make it publick, not out of any deſire to appear again in publick, but partly to vindicate my ſelf from the ſuſpicion of Popery, which I have been traduc'd for, partly by way of caution to others. Such as it is I willingly ſubmit to the Judgments of unprejudiced Readers; and that it may prove effectual for the vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of our Church from the falſe accuſations of its ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries is the hearty Prayers as well as deſires of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>R. S.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:154352:4"/>
            <p>
               <gap reason="missing" extent="1+ pages">
                  <desc>〈1… pages missing〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:154352:4"/>
            <p>Sacraments of the Lord. <hi>Auguſtine, Pſalm</hi> xxxii. Epiſt. 48. and 164. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> The peeviſh Schiſmaticks took advantage upon this their Conceſſion to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude themſelves to be the only Church, and to exclude all others. If it be ſo (ſay they) <hi>Communio noſtra eſt Eccleſia Chriſti.</hi> Our Communion is the Church of Chriſt alone. Aug. de Bapt. de cont. Donat. lib. 1. cap. 10. And <hi>Petilianus dixit, Petilian</hi> ſaith, Come to the Church, O people, and fly from the Traditors, if you will not periſh: that you may know they are guilty they judg rightly of our Faith, <hi>&amp;c. Contra lit. Pelit. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 1.8. If this reaſoning of <hi>Petilianus</hi> was good, then the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> Church it ſelf was excluded, if it was not, why does the <hi>Romaniſt</hi> uſe it againſt us? We muſt not do that to others we would not have others do to us.</p>
            <p>For that Argument the Doctor frames out of our Conceſſions towards the end of that Chapter,
'Tis very fallacious.</p>
            <p>The Church of God is but one.</p>
            <p>The Church of <hi>Rome</hi> is the True Church.</p>
            <p>The Church of <hi>England</hi> is oppoſite to that Church.</p>
            <p>Therefore the Church of <hi>England</hi> is no True Church.</p>
            <p>But not to trouble you with the vitioſity of his Logicks, I ſhall anſwer it as it lies.</p>
            <p>When we ſay the Church of God is but one, we mean the Univerſal Church, we ſpeak not Empha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tically
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:154352:5"/>or Excluſively, as if ſhe were the whole or the only Church, but we mean ſhe is a True parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Church. When we ſay the Church of <hi>England</hi> is oppoſite to the <hi>Roman</hi> Church, we mean <hi>Secun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum quid,</hi> in ſome things, not <hi>ſimpliciter,</hi> not ſimply in the Eſſentials of a Church, but in ſome Doctrins and Obſervations: In which reſpect ſome Church may be oppoſite to the <hi>Roman</hi> Church, and yet be a True Church ſtill as long as ſhe retains all the Fundamentals: As for example, one Doctor in the <hi>Roman</hi> Church may be oppoſite to another in ſome Opinions and Obſervations of Diſcipline, and yet be a True Catholick ſtill, as well as the other.</p>
            <p>A Second way whereby he pretends to end all Controverſies and prove the <hi>Roman</hi> Church to be the one Holy Catholick Church where Remiſſion of ſins is only, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Is by reference to a third party as Umpire in the buſineſs, and ſo he ſaith Proteſtants are caſt in their own Cauſe by the Arbitrement of St. <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> who being the Monarch of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, is Appealed to by both Parties as a competent Judg. Cap. 26.</p>
            <p>'Tis well the Doctor will acknowledg any Um<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire in the cauſe, but the Pope or the <hi>Roman</hi> Church. Surely this is a work of Supererogation, which he now does in a Bravado to ſhew what abundant ways he hath of confuting the poor Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> but he was not the Authour of this device. <hi>Ieronymus Torrenſis,</hi> a Jeſuite, many years ago abbre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viated
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:154352:5"/>all St. <hi>Auguſtines</hi> Works, and Publiſhed them in honour of his Church, by the name of <hi>Auguſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nina Confeſsio, Auguſtines</hi> Confeſſion. And <hi>Brerely</hi> a Prieſt contracted his Doctrine into a leſſer Model after him, and call'd it St. <hi>Auguſtines</hi> Religion. How much the Doctor is beholden to his two fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runners for their Collections, the world muſt not know, and 'tis no matter whether they do or no, if he can make it out by any means that St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> hath prejudged us ſo many hundred years ago, it muſt needs be a fatal blow to the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and this he endeavours to do by giving us St. <hi>Auguſtines</hi> Judgment in all or moſt of the parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars Controverted, but how truly you ſhall ſee in the ſequel.</p>
            <p>St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> (ſaith he) tells us plainly, that the Church was built upon <hi>Peter,</hi> in the firſt of his <hi>Retract. Cap.</hi> 21. Yet in this very firſt place, St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> he knows retracts it, and ſaith plainly by the Rock may be meant the Perſon, whom he confeſſed, it was not ſaid to him. <hi>Tues Petra, ſed tues Petrus, Petra autem erat Chriſtus, quem confeſſus Simon:</hi> Thou art the Rock, but thou art <hi>Peter,</hi> for the Rock was Chriſt whom <hi>Peter</hi> confeſſed, and though in the following words he leaves it to the choice of the Reader, to take which Interpretation he pleaſeth, yet by retracting of the former it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears he adhered to the latter. As is made more probable by another paſſage of the ſame Father in a
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:154352:6"/>Sermon <hi>de verb. Dom. Serm.</hi> 13. <hi>Non me ſuper te, Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tre, ſed te ſuper me,</hi> I am not built upon thee <hi>Peter,</hi> but thou upon me, and therefore in this point <hi>Pighius</hi> condemns that Father as inconſtant to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf.</p>
            <p>St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> acknowledged the Popes Suprema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, but not that unlimited Supremacy that is now challenged, conſiſting in a Superiority over Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cils, juriſdiction over Kings, in being Judg of all Controverſies, for St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> himſelf denyed Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peals to <hi>Rome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> (ſaith he) taught the Aſſumption of our Bleſſed Lady, her freedom from Original ſin, her vowed Chaſtity. But in that Book <hi>de Sancta Virginit.</hi> he refers us to, I find mention only of her vowed Chaſtity, which is no matter of Controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, but nothing of her freedom from Original ſin: and 'tis well known that Opinion of the Virgins freedom from Original ſin is of a later birth, it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing unknown in St. <hi>Bernards</hi> time, nothing deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined of it till the Council of <hi>Baſil.</hi> 1431.</p>
            <p>St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſaith that the Authority of the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick Church is of more efficacy than the word it ſelf; and we are of his Judgment too if he be rightly underſtood, that the Authority of the Church is of more efficacy to ſome, in ſome reſpect, to move Pagans and Infidels.</p>
            <p>St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> tells us 'tis an Heretical thing to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt only upon Scripture, and ſo ſay we, we know
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:154352:6"/>Reaſon muſt be uſed to convince Heathen, and Tradition to convince Hereticks.</p>
            <p>St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſaith that the Church cannot Err, ſo ſay we, if we underſtand by the Church, the Church Univerſal, with this limitation, in Fundamentals.</p>
            <p>St. <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> The Church of Chriſt is Univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal, and ſo ſay we: St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> tells us that the Church Catholick muſt be Viſible, ſo ſay we.</p>
            <p>St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> teacheth that there are Seven Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that's falſe, St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> no where ſpeaks of that juſt number, neither was it ever determined till the Council of <hi>Florence,</hi> nor heard of before <hi>Peter Lombard.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> (ſaith he) believed Tranſubſtantia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in effect, but not in terms: how does he know St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> believed it in effect, when he does not expreſs ſo much in his terms?</p>
            <p>St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> teacheth us that the Sacrament is to be adored, but in all the places he refers us to I can find nothing to that purpoſe, but only upon <hi>Pſalm</hi> xcvii. where he hath theſe words, <hi>Nemo carnem il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lam manducet niſi prius adoraverit,</hi> let no man Eat that Fleſh, unleſs he firſt adores, which I hope no good Chriſtian will refuſe to do. Chriſt no Queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ought to be adored in our approaches to that Sacrament, and the Sacrament it ſelf is venera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble; with all due reſpects to be handled and recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved.</p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:154352:7"/>
            <p>Not to trouble my ſelf nor you with examining all the Points of Divinity he gives us St. <hi>Auguſtines</hi> judgment on: if St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> taught the Euchariſt to be a Sacrifice: Confeſſion of ſins to a Prieſt: That Orders ought not to be conferr'd but by a Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop: That 'tis an Error to affirm a Biſhop and a Prieſt to be a like in Dignity. If he maintained Freewill: Juſtification by Works: That men are made Righteous by Works: For that was St. <hi>Auguſtines</hi> Notion of Juſtification. If he taught that good Works do Merit in ſome kind: the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence betwixt Venial and Mortal ſins: Preſcribed days of Faſting. If he commends Monaſtical life: The Learned of the Church of <hi>England</hi> will give their ſuffrage to St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> in all theſe parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars, and not betray their cauſe neither: So you ſee we have received no great damage by this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference yet.</p>
            <p>But if we turn over St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> again and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire out his judgment concerning the Innovati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and new Doctrines maintained in the <hi>Roman</hi> Church, we ſhall ſee that theſe Appellants them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves are condemned by St. <hi>Auguſtines</hi> Sentence.</p>
            <p>The preſent Church of <hi>Rome</hi> maintains Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipping of Images, St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> condemned it in his 119. Epiſt. <hi>ad Jan.</hi> ſaying, <hi>nulla imago ejus coli debet, &amp;c.</hi> no Image of God ought to be Worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped, but that which is the ſame with himſelf; and in his Book <hi>de moribus Eccleſiae. Cap.</hi> 34. he hath theſe
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:154352:7"/>words, Do not follow the rout of ignorant people, which in the true Religion are Superſtitious, I know many Worſhippers of Sepulchres and Pictures. And upon <hi>Pſalm</hi> cxii. he hath a long Diſcourſe to ſhew how dangerous the uſe of ſuch Images is.</p>
            <p>The preſent Church of <hi>Rome</hi> maintains that the Scriptures are imperfect and obſcure in matters of Faith and good Life, St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> teacheth the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary in his Book <hi>de Doctr. Chriſtiana,</hi> in thoſe things which are plainly delivered in the Scripture are found all things which concern Faith and good Life.</p>
            <p>The preſent Church denies the Scripture to be Judg of any Controverſie, St.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Collat. Carthag.</hi> 3. Cap. 187.</note> 
               <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſummons the <hi>Donatiſts</hi> to the Judgment of Scripture alone in that Controverſie, in one place he ſaith the Divine Teſtimonies alone are ſufficient to demonſtrate the Church: Let Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Authority alone ſpeak, let Scripture alone be produced, to which both of us owe ſubmiſſion. And in his Book <hi>de Unitate Eccleſiae,</hi> he ſaith, <hi>Non audiamus, haec dico, haec dicis, ſed audiamus, haec dicit Dominus, &amp;c.</hi> Let us not hear, this I ſay, and this thou ſayeſt, but let us hear, this the Lord ſaith: There are the Lords Books, let us there ſeek for the Church, let us there diſcuſs our cauſe, let thoſe things be laid aſide which we produce one againſt another not out of the Divine Canonical Books.</p>
            <p>The preſent <hi>Roman</hi> Church forbids people Read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Scripture, St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> exhorts his Audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:154352:8"/>all to Read the Scriptures, upon <hi>Pſalm</hi> xxxiii. Read the Scriptures (ſaith he) therefore God would have them written that we might be comforted.</p>
            <p>The preſent Church of <hi>Rome</hi> hath taken away the Cup from the people in the Sacrament, St. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine</hi> ſaith all the people muſt receive it, if they will have life. <hi>Quaeſt.</hi> 57. <hi>in Levit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The preſent Church of <hi>Rome</hi> maintains Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſubſtantiation, St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> denies it, in his Book againſt <hi>Adimantus,</hi> he hath theſe words, The Lord doubted not to ſay, this is my Body, when he gave a ſign of his Body: And in a Sermon upon <hi>Pſalm</hi> xcviii. he hath theſe words, <hi>Non hoc corpus, &amp;c.</hi> You are not about to Eat that Body, which you ſee, nor Drink that Bloud which is poured out by my Crucifiers. I have commended unto you a Sacrament, which being Spiritually underſtood ſhall quicken you, and although it be neceſſary to celebrate it viſibly, yet it ought to be underſtood inviſibly: it were an eaſie matter for a man mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly verſed in St. <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> to inſtance in many more particulars wherein that Father varies from the judgment of the preſent <hi>Roman</hi> Church. As concerning the number of the Sacraments, the Virgin <hi>Maries</hi> Immaculate Conception, Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers in an unknown Tongue, Purgatory, Invo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of Saints, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But I am weary and troubleſom, and ſo ſhall put a Period to this part, deſiring you now to judg impartially whether we
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:154352:8"/>be caſt in our cauſe by St. <hi>Auguſtines</hi> Sentence or no.</p>
            <p>The third way he pretends to end all Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſies, is by the known and ever acknowledged Tribunal, and Seat of Judgment provided in that behalf: and ſo Proteſtants are caſt in their own Cauſe again by Judiciary way of proceeding, by the higheſt Judicature in Cauſes Eccleſiaſtical: the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Arguments are not ſo plentiful with the Doctor as he makes ſhew of, when he is forced to make uſe of this new Topick, <hi>viz.</hi> to prove the <hi>Roman</hi> Church to be the whole Catholick Church, by the judgment of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church. If I bear witneſs of my ſelf (ſaith Chriſt) my witneſs is not true, <hi>John</hi> v. 31. <hi>Nemo qui de ſeipſo fert teſtimonium fide dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus eſt, propter ſuſpicionem de nimio ſui ipſius amore. Euthym.</hi> No body that bears witneſs of himſelf, is worthy to be believed, becauſe every man is ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected to love himſelf too well.</p>
            <p>And therefore whatſoever others may, this Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument is not like to ſway much with rational men, 'tis a poor thing of ſo great a Clerk, who hath ſo good a Cauſe as he conceives, and all learning of his ſide, to uſe ſuch pittiful begging of the Queſtion: Whether the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> be the Judg of all Controverſies is one thing in queſtion. And to Appeal to his Church as Judg, before he hath proved her to be ſo, is a piece of Sophiſtry.
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:154352:9"/>But this he makes us believe he hath done before in part, <hi>Cap.</hi> 1. and now he will do it more fully by Scriptures, Fathers <hi>Greek</hi> and <hi>Latin,</hi> the practice of all Ages, Nations, Tongues and People, and the confeſſion of her very Adverſaries. If he can do as much as he promiſeth, let him be Anathema Maranatha that ſhall not conform his judgment to the <hi>Roman</hi> Church, but if theſe be all Oſtentations, Rhodomontadoes to amaze his Reader and charm his Proſelytes into a Circle of ignorance. Hath not every wiſe man cauſe to ſuſpect that Cauſe that needs ſuch Arts to underprop it?</p>
            <p>Two things there are I ſuppoſe the Doctor is obliged to do to make this undertaking good.</p>
            <p>Firſt, to prove that the <hi>Roman</hi> Church is provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, and ordained by God the Judg of all Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſies, and ſo that ſhe is lawfully poſſeſt of this Office.</p>
            <p>Secondly, That, <hi>de facto,</hi> ſhe was ever acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged ſo to be.</p>
            <p>For the firſt he ſeems to do it by theſe Scriptures. God erected a ſtanding Judicature for all Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſies among the <hi>Jews, Deut.</hi> xvii. 8, 9. He fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tels that at Chriſts coming his Houſe ſhould be e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſhed on the top of the mountains, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſay</hi> ii. 2.</note> and all Nations ſhould flow unto it. Chriſt commands to hear the Church, <hi>Matth.</hi> xviii. and foretels that he will take the Kingdom of God from the <hi>Jews,</hi> and give it to another Nation, <hi>i. e.</hi> the
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:154352:9"/>
               <hi>Romans, Matth.</hi> xxi. 43. St. <hi>Paul</hi> tells us he hath given ſome Apoſtles, <hi>&amp;c. Epheſ.</hi> iv. 11. But theſe being all impertinent, and miſerably wreſted, I ſhall not waſt time and paper in anſwering them, and truly unleſs the Doctor had had more pertinent Texts to have proved the Queſtion, he ſhould have done well to have waved this kind of proof, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially ſeeing the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> hath not always claimed by this Title of Divine Right, when the conteſt was betwixt the <hi>Romans</hi> and <hi>Africans</hi> about Appeals: <hi>Zozimus, Bonifacius,</hi> and <hi>Celeſtinus</hi> the then Popes of <hi>Rome</hi> did not urge Divine Law for their claim of receiving Appeals out of <hi>Africa,</hi> but the Decrees of the <hi>Nicene</hi> Council, whereby it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears, that then they thought not that this Juriſdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction belonged to them by Divine Right.</p>
            <p>Yet this failing, if he can prove the matter of Fact it will be ſomthing, this is the Strength and Bulwark of the Cauſe, and this he ſeems to man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age with more dexterity: for very numerous he is in Quotation of Fathers, and very Rhetorical in perſuading, but his Authorities, if you obſerve them, are moſt of them impertinent; he produceth the te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimonies of the Fathers in great numbers to prove that the Pope of <hi>Rome</hi> was St. <hi>Peters</hi> Succeſſor, had magnificent Titles given him, was call'd a Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Biſhop, and Biſhop of the Catholick Church. That the <hi>Roman</hi> Church was in Ancient times very highly accounted of, that the <hi>Roman</hi> Faith was cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the Catholick Faith.</p>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:154352:10"/>
            <p>Only in the fixth Diviſion, <hi>Pag.</hi> 234. He ſeems to come home to the Queſtion: for there he gives us a juſt Catalogue of oppreſſed Biſhops that made complaints to the Pope of <hi>Rome,</hi> and of ſome Holy Fathers that made their addreſſes to him upon ſome other occaſions, which ſeem to argue that he was then acknowledged the Judg of all Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſies.</p>
            <p>This at firſt makes a great noiſe like the rat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of Hail upon a Houſe top, but ſoon falls to the Ground.</p>
            <p>The Pope of <hi>Rome</hi> may be conſidered in a three<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold capacity.</p>
            <p>Firſt, of a Biſhop over a particular Dioceſs, and ſo there belonged to him, as to other Biſhops, a Judgment of Juriſdiction over his own Clergy.</p>
            <p>Secondly, of a Patriarch, in which reſpect there belong'd to him Authority to hear complaints of Biſhops againſt their Metropolitans, and determine all differences amongſt Metropolitans under his Patriarchate.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, of the Prime Patriarch of the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick Church, without whoſe concurrence the meaner Patriarchs could do nothing in the weighty and important affairs of the Church, to whom the Cognizance of ſome things belonged above other Patriarchs, by the Canons of the Council of <hi>Sardis,</hi> and to whom ſingular honour was done, and ſome extraordinary Priviledges granted, as Biſhop of
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:154352:10"/>the Imperial City, as the Fathers of the Council of <hi>Chalcedon</hi> ſaid: in all which reſpects Complaints and Appeals might be made to the Pope of <hi>Rome,</hi> and yet it does not follow that he was ever acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg'd the Judg of all Controverſies. For 'tis evident notwithſtanding all the Priviledges of the Pope of <hi>Rome,</hi> that yet there was reſerved to every Biſhop the Judgment of all differences amongſt Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters in his own Dioceſs: To Metropolitans the Judgment of differences amongſt Biſhops: To Patriarchs the Judgment of Metropolitans: And to General Councils the Judgment of Patriarchs.</p>
            <p>And therefore for all this great flouriſh made by this Doctor in numbring ſo many Appellants, and Complainants to the Pope, I believe I am able to demonſtrate out of the Records of Antiquity, that the Pope of <hi>Rome</hi> was not ever acknowledged the Judg of all Controverſies.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Polycarpus</hi> was a bleſſed Martyr, and a Diſciple of St. <hi>John</hi> the Evangeliſt, and he did not acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg the Pope, nor the <hi>Roman</hi> Church, to be the Judg of all Controverſies, for be refuſed to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form to the Judgment of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church in the obſervation of <hi>Eaſter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Polycrates</hi> aſſembled with the <hi>Aſian</hi> Biſhops in a Synod did not acknowledg the <hi>Roman</hi> Church to be Judg of all Controverſies: For they ſtood in defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance with Pope <hi>Victor,</hi> and his Excommunication, about that Obſervation. <hi>Euſab. lib.</hi> 5. <hi>cap.</hi> 23.24.</p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:154352:11"/>
            <p>St. <hi>Cyprian</hi> was a Holy Martyr, and ſtand Cano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nized for a Saint in the <hi>Roman</hi> Church, and he did not acknowledg the <hi>Roman</hi> Church to be Judg of all Controverſies: For he did abrogate Appeals to <hi>Rome</hi> in the Cauſe of <hi>Fortunatus</hi> and <hi>Faeliciſsimus,</hi> and with a Council of Eighty Biſhops concluded contrary to the <hi>Roman</hi> Church in the buſineſs of Rebaptization, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 55. <hi>Ad Cornel.</hi>
               </note> as <hi>Bellar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine</hi> himſelf acknowledgeth. <hi>lib.</hi> 4. <hi>de Rom. Pont.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> was the Monarch of the Fathers, and ſo illuſtrious for Learning and Piety, that he is choſen by the Doctor to be Umpire in the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference: yet he did not acknowledg the <hi>Roman</hi> Church to be Judg of all Controverſies: For he in two Councils with the <hi>African</hi> Biſhops, <hi>viz.</hi> The <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> and the firſt Council of <hi>Carthage</hi> denyed Appeals to <hi>Rome</hi> in ſome caſes.</p>
            <p>It is true indeed, St. <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> in his 162. Epiſtle, does give us an account of the Judgment given by <hi>Melchiades,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> in the Controverſie be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt <hi>Donatus</hi> and <hi>Caecilianus,</hi> and does very highly extol and magnifie the Sentence of <hi>Melchiades,</hi> as in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed it deſerved to be. But withal he tells us that <hi>Melchiades</hi> did not aſſume to himſelf alone Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of Judging in that Caſe, but had many Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops of <hi>Italy,</hi> and <hi>France</hi> joyned with him.</p>
            <p>Inſomuch when <hi>Donatus</hi> refuſing to ſtand to the Judgment of <hi>Melchiades,</hi> and his Collegue Biſhops endeavoured to aſperſe and defame <hi>Melchiades,</hi>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:154352:11"/>St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> excuſeth him from all Arrogance and Uſurpation three ways: Firſt by declaring that they made him a Judg of that Controverſie, who Appealed unto him, and by their Prayers Sollici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted him to give Sentence in it, <hi>Judicem illi eum fece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt, &amp;c.</hi> they made him a Judg. Secondly, That the Emperour <hi>Conſtantine</hi> referred it to him, who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing petitioned ſent other Biſhops as Judges to ſit with him, and to determine what they found juſt in the matter. Thirdly, They knew they might have Appealed to a General Council, where if theſe Judges had been convinced to have Judged amiſs, their Sentence might have been reverſed, and the Judges themſelves Judged again.</p>
            <p>This Teſtimony is full enough to evince, that neither St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> nor the Age wherein he lived, acknowledged the <hi>Roman</hi> Church the Judg of all Controverſies.</p>
            <p>St. <hi>Jerom</hi> was a Mirror of Learning, and (as is pretended) a great aſſertor of the Popes Suprema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy: yet he did not acknowledg the Church off <hi>Rome</hi> to be Judg of all Controverſies: For in a great difference betwixt the Oriental Churches and the <hi>Roman</hi> Church in Point Doctrinal, he caſt off the Judgment of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church, and followed the <hi>Oriental.</hi> In St. <hi>Jeroms</hi> time the Epiſtle of St. <hi>Paul</hi> to the <hi>Hebrews</hi> was not received into the Canon of the Scripture by the <hi>Roman</hi> Church, but by the <hi>Eaſtern</hi> Churches it was: Now if the <hi>Roman</hi> Church
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:154352:12"/>had been acknowledged by him the Judg of all Controverſies, he would not, he durſt not have va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried from her, But he ſaith expreſly, <hi>Quod ſi La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tina Conſuetudo, &amp;c.</hi> Although the <hi>Latin</hi> Church doth not admit of the Epiſtle as Canonical, we notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding (ſaith he) do receive it. What need I add any more? If the Fathers acknowledged the <hi>Roman</hi> Church the Judg of all Controverſies, why did they take ſo much pains in confuting Hereſies by Scripture, by Tradition, when they might have ended all, by Appealing all to the Judgment of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church?</p>
            <p>In vain are ſo many means uſed for the compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of that, which might be done by fewer? And does not this Doctor himſelf tell us in Cap. 8. at the very beginning, of many Hereſies the Fathers ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed by Tradition alone, without the interpoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Judgment of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church. By this (ſaith he) <hi>Euſebius</hi> acknowledgeth <hi>Tertullian</hi> to have repreſſed the <hi>Marcionites: Irenaeus</hi> the <hi>Valentini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans:</hi> St. <hi>Cyprian</hi> the <hi>Novatians: Epiphanius</hi> the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolicks: St. <hi>Jerom</hi> the <hi>Helvidians:</hi> St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> the <hi>Donatiſts: Athanaſius</hi> the <hi>Arrians.</hi> How then in the mean time was the <hi>Roman</hi> Church the Judg of all Controverſies, and why may not Hereſies ſtill be ſuppreſſed that way?</p>
            <p>Now for the General Council, which this Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor names too, as favourers of this Juriſdiction in the <hi>Roman</hi> Chruch: 'Tis a very fond thing for any
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:154352:12"/>man to imagine that they ſhould contribute any thing to this aſſertion, when by ſo doing they had nulled their own Authority and Power. It is well known that General Councils were the higheſt Tribunals in the Church, that they gave Sentence in the weightieſt Controverſies, that they ſuppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Hereſies, depoſed Biſhops, Patriarchs, yea e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven Popes of <hi>Rome,</hi> and that the Popes of <hi>Rome</hi> themſelves for many years at their Inauguration ſwore to obſerve the Canons of the General Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cils. Now thus I argue, if the Judgment of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Differences and Controverſies did in a peculi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ar manner belong to General Councils: how is the <hi>Roman</hi> Church Judg of all Controverſies? If there did not: why were they aſſembled, and by what Authority did they theſe things before ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified?</p>
            <p>The fourth way of ending all Controverſies is by both Parties agreeing upon the ſame mark, whereby the thing in Conteſtation may be found out. And ſo (ſaith he, Cap. 28.) the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> is proved to be a true Church by the very ſame mark, which both Catholick and Proteſtants agree upon to be the mark of Chriſts Church.</p>
            <p>And if this be all the Doctor would have, who denies it? But I pray if that mark agreed upon on both ſides be of force to prove the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> to be a true Church: Is it of none to prove the Church of <hi>England</hi> to be ſo too, if found there?
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:154352:13"/>How comes this common mark to ſignifie ſo fully, when applyed to <hi>Roman</hi> Church, and to be as a Mute, and non-ſignificant, when applyed to the Church of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>'Tis ſtrange to ſee how in this Chapter he ſhuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fles, plays faſt and looſe, now gives, now takes away again. He begins with a deſignation of that mark of the Church, which (he ſaith) all agree upon. And that is Holineſs, which he takes in a new Notion for a Faithful Preaching of the Word, and Adminiſtration of the Sacraments, wherein all Scriptures Catholicks, Proteſtants agree; and yet in the very next place he undertakes to prove that faithful Preaching of Word, and Adminiſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Sacraments, whereof this Holineſs con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts, are no marks of the Church, and this he doth by two or three Arguments, <hi>Pag.</hi> 256. which if uſed againſt the fifteen marks of <hi>Bellarmines</hi> aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigning, would pare them all out of <hi>Roman</hi> Scutchi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. Now fearing he had done ſomthing he could not anſwer, he comes to ſalve all by a new diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of Holineſs.</p>
            <p>Holineſs (ſaith he) may be taken two ways. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 267.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, For an Univerſal purity of Doctrine, and true Preaching of the Word, as 'tis oppoſite to all errors in every Dogmatical and Eſſential Point.</p>
            <p>Secondly, For a particular diſcerning Holineſs, whereby the true Preaching of the Word is oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:154352:13"/>to all palpable and groſs abſurdities, repugnant to the very Principles of Nature, Rules of Faith, and expreſs Texts of Scripture.</p>
            <p>What the meaning of this diſtinction is, I confeſs, I underſtand not, nor I believe he himſelf; if he were injoy'd to make it intelligible, and juſtifie it by the Rules of Art, I believe it would coſt him more pains than the writing of his Book. After he hath told us of this miraculous diſtinction, which no man knows to what purpoſe, he advanceth to the great works, <hi>viz.</hi> To prove the <hi>Roman</hi> Church to be a True Church by thoſe marks, which are no marks.</p>
            <p>We will conſider (ſaith he) on our ſide what Doctrine it is which the <hi>Roman</hi> Catholicks do Preach: and on the other ſide what Doctrine it is which the Proteſtants maintain: and comparing both together, obſerve whether of the two Preach more ſincerely or faithfully.</p>
            <p>For the Catholicks (ſaith he) they preſcribe a ſtrict way by Confeſſing of ſins, doing Pennance, Reſtitution for wrong done, ſet-times of Faſting, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But the Proteſtants the clean contrary.</p>
            <p>If the Proteſtants taught all things, he would make the world believe, they do, they were very monſters of men, not fit to live in the World. But we that know what we Preach as well as he, proclaim to the world, that we Preach Confeſſion of ſins, doing Pennance, Reſtitution for wrong done, Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tification,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:154352:14"/>Set-times of Faſting, contempt of the World, Self-denyal, Chaſtity Virginal, Vidual, Marital, and all other things neceſſary to be belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved and done for Salvation. What if ſome Secta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian Zelots amongſt us teach the contrary? How does this concern the Church of <hi>England,</hi> who in Juſtice ſtands not bound to maintain, or anſwer for all the wild and mad opinions of them, that ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate from her. And therefore 'tis not fair dealing in this Doctor, to make the world believe we hold all things contrary to ſound Doctrine, much worſe to father upon the Church of <hi>England</hi> all the looſe, furious, ſpurious Principles of all that ſtand in op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition to <hi>Rome.</hi> What have we to do with the intemperate ſpeeches of <hi>Luther,</hi> or the new Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of the Lemanical Dictator, who follow none but Chriſt and the Primitive Catholick Church?</p>
            <p>But grant that the Church of <hi>England</hi> ſhould not Preach the Doctrine of Chriſt ſo ſincerely as the <hi>Roman</hi> Church does, how does it follow upon this, that the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> is the only True Church, and the Church of <hi>England</hi> none? 'Tis a Rule in Logick, that <hi>magis &amp; minùs non variant ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciem:</hi> that more or leſs Intention or Remiſſion does not vary, or diverſifie the kind. If the Church of <hi>England</hi> do Preach Chriſts Doctrine ſo ſincerely, as to Preach it ſufficiently for mans Salvation, all things neceſſary for mans Salvation, though the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:154352:14"/>Church Preach it more excellently. The Church of <hi>England</hi> may be a True Church ſtill: For there are degrees of the ſincere Preaching, and profeſſion of Chriſts Doctrine. One conſiſting in a freedom from all errours, and that is not neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarily required to the being of a Church. Another conſiſting in a freedom from all pertinacious error. And 'tis this laſt we make a note of the Church; a ſincerity free from all pertinacious error, and in this degree of ſincerity the Church of <hi>England</hi> does profeſs to Preach Chriſts Doctrine, and by ſo doing is a True Church.</p>
            <p>The ſecond Mark that Proteſtants make of the True Church, is the lawful Adminiſtration of the Sacraments, whereby he undertakes in Cap. 30. to prove the Church of <hi>England</hi> to be no True Church. At firſt he Scoptically mentions it, calling it an Ear-mark, although as wiſe and as learned a man as himſelf, <hi>Alexander Ales,</hi> made it ſo in good earneſt. At laſt he himſelf makes uſe of it to prove the Church of <hi>England</hi> to be no True Church, <hi>viz.</hi> becauſe the Church of <hi>England</hi> neither adminiſters all the Sacraments, which are Seven, nor holds it neceſſary all ſhould be adminiſtred: nor acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgeth all to be Sacraments, which is contrary to expreſs Text of Scripture, and the Word of God.</p>
            <p>A high degree of contumacy, and perverſneſs, if True, and enough to ſtigmatize us to all Ages. But if the Church of <hi>England</hi> allow all to be Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:154352:15"/>that are ſo, and the number of Seven Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in that ſence, the Ancient Church call'd them ſo, though amongſt them two more chief, and ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally neceſſary to Salvation: What degree of Hereſie is this?</p>
            <p>For the word Sacrament we know it is an Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtical word, and in the power of the Church to impoſe upon what holy Signs or Ceremonies ſhe pleaſeth. And if the Antient Church have thought it fitting to call thoſe Holy Actions mention'd in the the Scripture, with that name, as Confirmation, Holy Orders, Matrimony, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> we oppoſe it not, we commend the moderation of <hi>Melancthon,</hi> who thinks this no juſt matter of quarrel. But 'tis well known that the word Sacrament was uſed two ways by the Antients.</p>
            <p>Firſt largely, for any Holy ſecret, or ſign of any Holy ſecret. So <hi>Tertullian</hi> calls Chriſtianity it ſelf a Sacrament, <hi>lib.</hi> 4. <hi>contra Marcion,</hi> and in his Fifth Book ſpeaking of <hi>Abrahams</hi> Sons, he calls them <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramenta figuram,</hi> the Sacraments of figures, and in his Book againſt the <hi>Jews;</hi> he calls the Hatchet of <hi>Eliah, Sacramentum ligni,</hi> the Sacrament of the wood.</p>
            <p>Somtimes ſtrictly, for a Holy ſecret, Symboli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally ſignifying, and Sealing ſome Spiritual Grace, and Ordained by Chriſt for that purpoſe. And ſo they eſteem'd Baptiſm, and the Euchariſt, Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in a more excellent manner.</p>
            <pb n="31" facs="tcp:154352:15"/>
            <p>But to go no further than the words of the Doctor, p. 287. where he defines a Sacrament to be a viſible ſign of an inviſible Grace Divinely In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted for our Sanctification. How will the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor by this Definition prove all the Seven to be True Proper Sacraments, when Five of them want Divine Inſtitution, or matter and form Eſſential to Sacraments.</p>
            <p>To inſtance in Confirmation, they acknowledg themſelves there is no command of Chriſt for it, but only the Example of the Apoſtles. The mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, they ſay, of this Sacrament is Holy <hi>Chriſm</hi> Confect, and made of Oyl Olive and Balm Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecrated by a Biſhop: the Form is the words of the Biſhop, <hi>I ſign thee with the ſign of the Croſs,</hi> now no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of theſe is determined by Chriſt. <hi>Alexander Ales</hi> ſaith it was Ordained in the Councel of <hi>Melden. Durandus</hi> denyes Matrimony to be a True and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Sacrament of the new Law, becauſe it neither confers Grace to him that hath it not, nor augments it in him that hath it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Cajetan</hi> upon the fifth Chapter of St. <hi>James,</hi> verſe 14. ſaith that there is nothing at all ſpoken there for the Sacrament of Extream Unction. And ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſome of theſe Sacraments according to their own Doctors want Divine Inſtitution, ſome Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Efficacy to Sanctifie, ſome matter and form Eſſential to Sacraments, 'tis clear they are not of that excellency and perfection that Baptiſm and
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:154352:16"/>the Euchariſt are; and therefore what Hereſie is it in the Church of <hi>England</hi> to receive them as more chiefly, and generally neceſſary to Salvation, ſo long as ſhe acknowledgeth the other to be Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in that ſenſe the Antient Church call'd them ſo, <hi>vid. Lyran. in explic. viſionis, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The fifth and laſt way whereby he pretends to put an end to Controverſies, is by Combat, by anſwering the Challenge, which ſome of the Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned of the Church of <hi>England</hi> have made to them of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church, to be tryed by the Teſtimony of the Fathers that lived within the time of the firſt ſix hundred years of Chriſt. This Challenge was made (ſaith he) by Biſhop <hi>Jewel</hi> in a Sermon at <hi>Pauls</hi> Croſs, and by Dr. <hi>Whitaker</hi> in his Reaſons a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Campian.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Though we of the Church of <hi>England</hi> are no ways bound to defend what every private Doctor ſhall Preach in a Sermon, or let fall from his Pen in heat of Controverſie, yet I believe verily, a man may become a Second to theſe Champions in this Duel, and yet come off without broken Bones: though for my part I confeſs my ſelf altogether un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able for ſuch an undertaking, yet out of my little Learning I am able to diſcover a great deal of foul play the Doctor uſeth at the firſt, which makes me think that he himſelf is not very able to hold up the Bucklers in this quarrel neither.</p>
            <pb n="33" facs="tcp:154352:16"/>
            <p>For in ſtating the quarrel betwixt the two Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>batants, he reckons up three and twenty points of Divinity as Controverted betwixt them, whereas eighteen of theſe are not Controverted by the Church of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For the firſt, we maintain no Free-Will.</p>
            <p n="2">2. We hold that Free-Will Cooperates with Grace.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That Good Works do in ſome kind Merit.</p>
            <p n="4">4. We maintain the Faſt of <hi>Lent</hi> to be very An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient, Good, and requiſite to be obſerved.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Concerning Original ſin we receive all that is determined by Antient Church againſt the <hi>Pelagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6. We teach Good Works are required to Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication.</p>
            <p n="7">7. That a man ought to be ſure of his Predeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation is no Doctrine of the Church of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="8">8. We teach that a man fall away after Baptiſm.</p>
            <p n="9">9. Concerning Chriſt the Mediatour, we hold as the <hi>Roman</hi> Church, that he was Mediatour in both his Natures, but ſuffered only in his human.</p>
            <p n="10">10. We believe Chriſt deſcended into Hell.</p>
            <p n="11">11. We teach that Chriſts Law and Precepts are poſſible to be kept.</p>
            <p n="12">12. Concerning Veneration of Reliques, if we had any which we were ſure were genuine, we would not doubt to give ſome Veneration towards them.</p>
            <pb n="34" facs="tcp:154352:17"/>
            <p n="13">13. We allow Prayer for the dead in reſpect of the Reſurrection. In a word we deny not Church Traditions, that are genuine, nor the Efficacy of the Sacraments, nor the neceſſity of Baptiſm, nor Confeſſion, and Abſolution, nor the Sacrifice of the Holy Euchariſt.</p>
            <p>And for thoſe other five points, wherein we profeſs to recede from the <hi>Roman</hi> Church, we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare unto the World, if they were received in the <hi>Roman</hi> Church only in that degree of credibility they were taught by the Antients, we ſhould not look upon them as ſuch Terriculaments as we do, when the Antients taught them only as probable Opinions, and the <hi>Roman</hi> Church hath now made them Articles of Faith: <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Can.</hi> 7.</note> we think 'tis time for us to remember that Canon of the great Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil of <hi>Epheſus</hi> which pronounceth Anathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma againſt all thoſe that ſhall compoſe any other Creed beſides the <hi>Nicene.</hi> Which of the Antients in the firſt ſix hundred years did receive or teach Purgatory, or Invocation of Saints as Articles of their Creed?</p>
            <p>Another piece of foul play I obſerve in this Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puter, is this, that in ſtating of the quarrel betwixt the <hi>Roman</hi> Church and the Church of <hi>England,</hi> he does not only ſhuffle in many things which were never in queſtion, but does alſo leave out all thoſe things which make up the Wall of Separation be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt us. As firſt the unlimited Supremacy of the
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:154352:17"/>Pope. 2. The Infallibility of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church. 3. The Worſhip of Images. 4. The Sacrament in one kind. 5. Prayer in an unknown Tongue, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Theſe are the <hi>Gravamina</hi> we complain of, theſe are the Rocks of Offence we ſtumble at, which unleſs he can prove by the Teſtimony of the Antients, as well at the other, he doth but fight with his own ſhadow, and as they ſay <hi>fingere ſtolidum ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſarium,</hi> and then <hi>ſugillare,</hi> make to himſelf a fooliſh Adverſary, and then beat him. I ſhall end with that Counſel St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> gives the <hi>Donatiſt: Auferte perditam ſimulationem, ſi de moribus non vultis, ſaltem de literis veſtris,</hi> take away the wicked diſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulation, if ye will not from your manners, do it at leaſt from your writings.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:154352:18"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:154352:18"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:154352:19"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:154352:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
